地球脉动 Ⅲ
第八集
翻译：弥禾
(低无线电干扰)
LOW RADIO CHATTER
大卫·爱登堡:这些人在打猎
DAVID ATTENBOROUGH: These people are hunting
地球上最濒危的动物之一.
for one of the most endangered animals on the planet.
黑犀牛--一种因角而被偷猎的动物.
The black rhino - an animal poached for its horn.
(枪声)
GUN FIRES
但他们不会伤害她。
But they aren't going to harm her.
杜米·兹瓦内 (Dumi Zwane) 和他的团队正在执行救援任务。
Dumi Zwane and his team are on a rescue mission.
杜米:我想我永远不会停止为犀牛而战。
DUMI: I don't think I'll ever stop fighting for rhino.
这是不可能的。
It's just not possible.
好的！ 是的...
OK! Yeah...
他们正在一个安全的避风港建立一个新的繁殖群。
They're setting up a new breeding colony in a safe haven.
让她穿两件。
Get her on two.
二。 好的。 那挺好的。
Two. OK. That's good.
这位女性将处于这一切的中心。
This female is going to be at the very centre of it.
她的体重有一吨多...
She weighs over a tonne...
去！
Go!
……只有一种方法可以让她出去。
..and there's only one way to get her out.
就是这样。
That's it.
我们到了。 完美的！
There we are. Perfect!
当我看着它飞走的时候，我的心情非常激动。
When I watch it fly off, it's very emotional.
这是一种美好的感觉。
It's a beautiful feeling.
她已经服用了镇静剂并且很安全......
She is sedated and safe...
......不到半小时，她就会回到地面
...and in less than half an hour, she'll be back on the ground
并在一个可以拯救她整个物种的项目中开始新的生活，
and starting a new life in a project that could save her entire species,
感谢杜米和他出色的团队。
thanks to Dumi and his remarkable team.
家园卫士
解说
大卫·爱登堡
我们开始制作第一个《地球脉动》系列
We started making the very first Planet Earth series
就在20多年前。
just over 20 years ago.
从那时起，我们的摄影团队在世界各地进行拍摄
Since then, our camera teams have filmed all over the world
并参观了一些最荒凉、最偏远的角落。
and visited some of its wildest and most remote corners.
但事实是我们拍摄的大多数动物
But the truth is that most of the animals we filmed
在过去的二十年里，现在比以前更加罕见了。
over these last two decades are now rarer than they were.
以及他们居住的地方
And the places where they live
面临更大的破坏危险。
are in greater danger of destruction.
但那些年我看到了另一个变化
But I've seen another change in those years,
一个充满希望的改变。
a hopeful change.
新一代杰出人士正在挺身而出
A new generation of remarkable people are stepping up
拯救野生动物。
to save wildlife.
他们正在克服巨大的障碍，
They're overcoming huge obstacles,
去危险的地方旅行，
travelling to dangerous places,
有时甚至冒着生命危险。
and sometimes even risking their lives.
对我来说，他们是真正的英雄。
To me, they are true heroes.
这是其中一些人的故事。
This is the story of some of them.
隐藏在安第斯山脉的中心
Hidden in the heart of the Andes
是 Centro Jambatu 研究中心。
is the Centro Jambatu research centre.
它保护的是，也许令人惊讶的是，
It's protecting members of what is, perhaps surprisingly,
世界上最濒临灭绝的动物群。
the most endangered group of animals in the world.
青蛙。
Frogs.
这些个体是其特定物种的最后一个。
These individuals are the very last of their particular species.
他们被带到这里不仅是为了保护，
They're brought here not only for protection,
但更重要的是，
but, more importantly,
来增加他们的数量。
to increase their numbers.
还有找到他们的人...
And the person to find them...
..海梅·库莱布拉斯。
..Jaime Culebras.
我七岁时第一次看到青蛙
I was seven the first time that I saw a frog
改变了我的生活。
and just changed my life.
而且从他小时候起，
And ever since his childhood,
他一直在探索最偏远的地方
he's been exploring the remotest places
并寻找最稀有的青蛙。
and searching for the rarest frogs.
这是一只叶蛙。
This is a leaf frog.
他真是太棒了。
He is just amazing.
不可能不爱上这样的动物，不是吗？
It's impossible to don't fall in love with an animal like this, no?
但这里有一只非常特别的青蛙。
But there is one frog here that is very special.
他的名字是悲伤的圣地亚哥。
His name, Sad Santiago.
这是悲伤的圣地亚哥。
This is Sad Santiago.
他很伤心，因为他孤身一人。
He's sad because he's alone.
他是该物种最后的成员之一。
He's one of the last members of his species.
而且他需要一个女性。
And he needs a female.
被称为莫罗纳-圣地亚哥丑角蛙，
Known as the Morona-Santiago harlequin frog,
他可能是世界上最稀有的青蛙。
he may be the rarest frog in the world.
当这里的其他青蛙正在尽力而为时
While the other frogs here are doing their best
为了增加他们的人口，
to increase their populations,
圣地亚哥已经独自坐了四年了。
Santiago has sat alone for four long years.
也许它不是最美丽的青蛙，但他值得被爱。
Maybe it's not the most beautiful frog, but he deserves love.
圣地亚哥现在已经老了，
Santiago has now grown old,
如果詹姆不能很快找到一个女人给他，
and if Jaime can't find a female for him soon,
整个物种可能会灭绝。
the whole species could become extinct.
雷霆隆隆
THUNDER RUMBLES
最后一次看到这些青蛙的地方......
The last place where one of these frogs was seen...
..在厄瓜多尔云雾森林的一座高山上。
..was high up on a mountain in the cloud forest of Ecuador.
只有一种方法可以到达那里。
There's only one way to get there.
驴子喷鼻息
DONKEY SNORTS
加入他行列的是青蛙猎人达尔文
Joining him is fellow frog-hunter Darwin
还有海梅的搭档兼青蛙科学家弗朗西斯卡。
and Jaime's partner and frog scientist, Francesca.
哦！
Oh!
来吧，瓦马诺斯。
Come on, vamanos.
阿里巴。
Arriba.
弗朗西斯卡:这是地球上最潮湿的地方之一，
FRANCESCA: This is one of the wettest places on Earth,
现在实际上是雨季，雨季，
and right now it's actually the wet season, the rainy season,
所以雨下得更大了。
so it rains even more.
浑身湿透，还爬满了虫子……
Soaking wet and teeming with bugs...
..对于青蛙来说，这是一个完美的地方。
..it's a perfect place for frogs.
我们走吧。
Let's go.
大多数青蛙都会在晚上从躲藏处出来。
Most frogs come out of hiding at night.
这个地方非常美妙。
This place is extremely wonderful.
但你必须小心你的手放在哪里。
But you have to be careful where you put your hands.
和他在一起就是...
Being with him is...
..这很不寻常。
..it's unusual.
这不是你们之间的正常关系。
It's not your regular relationship.
她笑了
SHE LAUGHS
哦，他着迷了。 他真的很着迷。
Oh, he's obsessed. He's really obsessed.
像这样的溪流应该充满青蛙
Streams like this should be full of frogs
许多不同物种的...
of many different species...
..但他们搜查了一夜却一无所获。
..but they search all night and find nothing.
这是一片寂静的森林。
It's a silent forest.
这是可悲的。
It's sad.
青蛙的声音正在慢慢从我们的世界消失。
The sound of frogs is slowly disappearing from our world.
现在唯一可以找到多种青蛙的地方
The only place many frog species can now be found
在博物馆里。
is in a museum.
一个关键原因是一种叫做壶菌的真菌的传播......
A key reason is the spread of a fungus called chytrid...
..可以在青蛙潮湿的皮肤上生长，
..that can grow on the moist skins of frogs,
最终杀死他们。
eventually killing them.
据信有 90 个物种因此灭绝，
90 species are thought to have become extinct as a consequence,
目前还有近 600 种濒临灭绝的物种。
and almost 600 more are now critically endangered.
在壶菌出现之前，我很确定你可以走路
Before chytrid, I'm pretty sure that you could walk
穿过溪流，到处可见
through the stream and see everywhere
岩石上有很多很多青蛙，
many, many, many frogs on the rocks,
呼叫“呜呜呜”！
calling   prrr-prrr  !
我希望我是在青蛙病爆发之前出生的。
I wish I had been born before the frog disease.
一夜又一夜...
Night after night...
..他们搜索流。
..they search the stream.
海梅！
Jaime!
终于有一个发现了。
At last, there is a discovery.
声音是一...
The sound is a...
杰米·特里尔斯
JAIME TRILLS
我不知道具体在哪里，但或多或??少就在那里。
I don't know exactly where, but it's there, more or less.
在水中！
En el agua!
我们有它。
We have it.
一只玻璃青蛙。
A glass frog.
一只非常漂亮的玻璃青蛙。
A really beautiful glass frog.
玻璃蛙变得越来越稀有，
Glass frogs are becoming increasingly rare,
有一天，它们也可能消失。
and one day they, too, could disappear.
但这不是他们想要的。
But it's not what they are looking for.
事实是无数的物种灭绝了......
The fact is that countless species go extinct...
..未被注意到。
..unnoticed.
海梅能做的就是继续他的寻找
All Jaime can do is to continue his search
为圣地亚哥找个伴侣。
for a mate for Santiago.
在那里？
It's there?
我发现了一个女的！
I found a female!
啊啊！
Agh!
呜呼！
Woohoo!
是个女的！ 看。
It's a female! Look.
体型比雄性大。
The size is bigger than the males.
哇。
Wow.
我很高兴！
I feel so happy!
第一女！
The first female!
她可能成为新育种计划的基石。
She could be the cornerstone of a new breeding programme.
圣地亚哥会非常非常非常非常高兴。
Santiago will be very, very, very, very, very happy.
詹姆笑了
JAIME LAUGHS
因为她真的很美！
Because she's really beautiful!
我的手中，充满了希望。
In my hand, I have hope.
我有这个物种的救星，
I have the saviour of this species,
用于育种计划和人们繁殖它。
for breeding programmes and for people to reproduce it.
我不知道，好像我手里还抱有希望。
I don't know, it's like I just have hope in my hand.
世界上有7000多种青蛙，
There are over 7,000 species of frogs in the world,
你可能会问...
and you may well ask...
..如果有一些灭绝了，真的很重要吗？
..does it really matter if a few go extinct?
好吧，看看这个微小的物种
Well, just look at this tiny species
的毒箭蛙。
of poison arrow frog.
科学家在它的皮肤上发现了一种化学物质......
Scientists discovered a chemical on its skin...
..比吗啡强200倍。
..200 times stronger than morphine.
现在他们正在研究如何创造强大的新型止痛药。
Now they are studying how it works to create powerful new painkillers.
但自然世界不仅仅是一个巨大的药箱。
But the natural world is not just one vast medicine chest.
远不止于此。
It's far more than that.
它是我们的生命维持系统，
It is our life support system,
将我们的世界凝聚在一起的织物。
the fabric that holds our world together.
移除它的一部分，一个物种或一个栖息地，
Remove a part of it, a species or a habitat,
不知道会发生什么。
and there's no knowing what could happen.
低沉的隆隆声
LOW RUMBLING
一个典型的例子是森林象。
A prime example is the forest elephant.
他们在维护方面发挥着至关重要的作用
They play a crucial role in maintaining
非洲的雨林...
the rainforests of Africa...
大象喇叭
ELEPHANT TRUMPETS
..撒播种子并清理空地
..dispersing seeds and making clearings
然后被许多其他动物使用。
that are then used by many other animals.
我们在 2004 年拍摄了这些照片
We filmed these images in 2004
第一部《地球脉动》系列。
for the first Planet Earth series.
大象喇叭
ELEPHANT TRUMPETS
九年后，偷猎者来到这里
Nine years later, poachers came here
并为了象牙而杀死了26头大象......
and killed 26 elephants for their ivory...
..包括四头小牛。
..including four of the calves.
自从第一个系列以来，
Since that first series,
非洲森林象的数量
the number of forest elephants across Africa
已经下降了三分之二。
has dropped by two-thirds.
但制止屠杀是一件危险的事情。
But stopping the slaughter is a risky business.
阿比让，西非科特迪瓦...
Abidjan, in Cote d'Ivoire, West Africa...
..全球非法象牙贸易网络的一部分。
..part of the global network in the illegal ivory trade.
一个陌生人从越南飞来，
A stranger has flown in from Vietnam,
象牙进口中心。
a hub for the import of ivory.
她的名字是--Trang Nguyen。
Her name - Trang Nguyen.
她的专长--渗透非法野生动物贸易
Her speciality - infiltrating the illegal wildlife trade
冒充买家。
by posing as a buyer.
Trang 正在与一个名为 EAGLE 的自然资源保护主义者网络合作。
Trang is working with a network of conservationists called EAGLE.
她的联系人是 Rens Ilgen。
Her contact here is Rens Ilgen.
但西非这一新贸易的特别之处在于，
But what is particular with this new trade in West Africa is,
正如你所看到的，很多象牙都来自小象。
as you can see, a lot of the tusks are from baby elephants.
所以，他们真的只剩下最后一头大象了。
So, they're really down to the last elephants.
上周，有七人死亡。
Last week, seven people were killed.
七游侠被杀？
Seven ranger was killed?
所以，很明显，这不仅仅是象牙贸易的问题，
So, clearly, it is not just about the ivory trade,
但很多人，护林员，也被杀害。
but a lot of people, rangers, that are being killed as well.
这是……这是战争。 这是战争。
It's...it's war. It's war.
他们甚至还去寻找小象。 是的。
And they're even going for the baby elephants. Yeah.
现在，Trang 已经确定了她的任务。
Now Trang is set her task.
所以，我想让你见见象牙教父。
So, I want you to meet the godfather of ivory.
我们四年前就已经逮捕了他
We already arrested him four years ago
当他拥有400公斤象牙时，
when he had 400kg of ivory,
他向越南社区提供的
which he was supplying to the Vietnamese community
与越南黑手党有联系。
linked to the Vietnamese mafia.
由于他以前被捕过，所以他可能会非常谨慎。
As he has been arrested before, he might be very cautious.
这可能很危险。
It might be dangerous.
她准备伪装成一名女商人--
She prepares her disguise as a businesswoman -
但在她的夹克下面，
but under her jacket,
隐藏的录音设备。
hidden recording equipment.
EAGLE 的卧底特工一直在跟踪
EAGLE's undercover agents have been following
教父多年。
the godfather for years.
现在是抓住他的时候了。
Now is the moment to catch him.
这是你们第一次见面。
This is your first meeting.
你们只是要讨论并互相了解。
You're just going to discuss and get to know each other.
看看他们有没有产品。 确切地。
See if they have the products. Exactly.
我要进去，
I'm going in,
我需要背对门坐着，
and I need to sit facing away from the door,
因为我不想让别人看到我和他在一起。
because I don't want people to see me with him.
我们就在附近...是的。
We will be close by... Yep.
..并且不会出错。
..and nothing will go wrong.
好的。
OK.
祝你好运。
Good luck.
再见。
Bye.
她在当地的一家咖啡馆遇见了教父。
She meets the godfather at a local cafe.
秘密摄像机捕捉到了这个故事。
The secret cameras capture the story.
庄:嗯嗯。
TRANG: Mm-hm.
但教父否认有任何象牙可供出售。
But the godfather denies having any ivory for sale.
庄:谢谢。
TRANG: Merci.
耶耶耶。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
谢谢。
Merci.
也许没有象牙。
Perhaps there's no ivory.
或者也许他不信任Trang。
Or maybe he doesn't trust Trang.
这是一个严重的挫折。
It's a serious setback.
但还有其他交易者。
But there are other traders out there.
也许她出现在城里会吸引他们。
Perhaps her presence in town will draw them in.
过去的每一天，
Every day that passes,
更多的大象被杀死。
more elephants are killed.
对于 Trang 来说，这部作品非常个人化。
For Trang, this work is very personal.
当我23岁的时候，我接到了电话。
When I was 23, I got the phone call.
医生告诉我，我患有肠癌。
The doctor told me that I had bowel cancer.
我脑子里第一个闪现的就是我还年轻
The first thing pop up in my mind is that I'm so young,
那么，我怎么会得癌症呢？
well, how can I get cancer?
一旦患上癌症，
Once you have cancer,
你不知道自己还能活多久
you don't know how long you're going to live for,
如果我想做任何事，那么我现在就应该做。
and if I want to do anything, then I should just do it now.
就在那时我说:“好吧，我要做卧底”
And that's when I said,   OK, I'm just going to do undercover,
因为我不知道我什么时候会死。
because I don't know when I'm going to die.
我还不如做一些真正有意义的事情。
I might as well do something really meaningful.
目前，Trang 处于缓解期。
Currently, Trang is in remission.
三天后，事情有了突破。
Three days later, there's a breakthrough.
电话 PING
PHONE PINGS
交易员发送的视频。
A video sent by a trader.
我可以看到这个视频有大约14、15颗象牙。
I can see that this video have about 14, 15 ivory.
它们是大象牙，也是小象牙。
They are big tusks, they are also small tusks as well.
它显然来自小象。
It's obviously come from baby elephants.
诱饵已经上钩了。
The bait has been taken.
Trang 和 EAGLE 团队必须迅速采取行动。
Trang and the EAGLE team must act fast.
她要去实现新的目标。
She goes to meet the new targets.
第一份工作...
First job...
庄:晚安。
TRANG: Bonsoir.
..赢得他们的信任。
..gain their trust.
干杯。
Cheers.
干杯。 干杯。
Cheers. Cheers.
庄说英语:
TRANG SPEAKING ENGLISH:
交易员:好的。
TRADER: OK.
最终，Trang 说服商人搬到
Eventually, Trang persuades the traders to move to
附近的一个酒店房间...
a hotel room nearby...
..称量象牙并进行交易。
..to weigh the ivory and make the transaction.
庄:把门关上。 关门。
TRANG: Close the door. Close the door.
象牙按公斤出售。
Ivory is sold by the kilo.
TRANG:刚刚超过20个。
TRANG: That is just over 20.
20.2？
20.2?
交易员:20.3。
TRADER: 20.3.
为了这次运输，整个大象家族被杀。
A whole elephant family was killed for this haul.
低语气
LOW CHATTER
它的价值超过 5,000 英镑。
It's worth over ?5,000.
在这里，这是一年的工资。
Here, that is a year's salary.
交易者没有意识到的...
What the traders don't realise...
..警察就在楼上的房间里吗？
..is that the police are in the room above,
等待 Trang 的短信。
waiting for a text from Trang.
轻声:好吧，我们走吧。
SOFTLY: OK, let's go.
耳语
WHISPERING
敲门
KNOCK ON DOOR
庄:谁在那儿？
TRANG: Who's there?
服务？
Service?
庄:你去开门吧。
TRANG: You go open the door.
交易员:好的。
TRADER: OK.
安静地:把它放在这儿吧。
QUIETLY: Just put it down here.
警察！ 警察！
Police! Police!
庄尖叫
TRANG SCREAMS
别动，别动，别动！
Don't move, don't move, don't move!
庄尖叫
TRANG SCREAMS
庄说法语:
TRANG SPEAKING FRENCH:
为了她自己的安全，
For her own safety,
她必须保留她的掩护故事并表现得像个罪犯......
she has to keep her cover story and behave as a criminal...
低声喊叫
MUFFLED SHOUTING
..这意味着她也必须被捕。
..which means she must also be arrested.
警方发布命令
POLICE ISSUE ORDERS
全球供应链中的一个环节...
A link in the global supply chain...
..破碎的。
..broken.
Trang被带走了，
Trang is whisked away,
当商贩被带到警察局时，
whilst the traders are taken to the police station,
没人知道她的参与。
none the wiser about her involvement.
明年，EAGLE 又抓获 140 名毒贩
Over the next year, EAGLE catch 140 more traffickers
打击全球野生动物贸易。
in the fight against the global wildlife trade.
但对于Trang来说，这是她的最后一次手术。
But for Trang, this is her last operation.
这就是为什么我们可以展示她的脸。
It's why we can show her face.
对她来说，多待一分钟是不安全的。
It's not safe for her to stay a minute longer than necessary.
Trang 的最终任务是从阿比让消失……
Trang's final task is to vanish from Abidjan...
..永远。
..for ever.
在世界各地，野生动物的数量正在惊人地下降。
Across the world, the numbers of wild animals are falling alarmingly.
短短二十年--
In just two decades -
自从我们开始制作第一个《地球脉动》系列以来 -
since we started making the first Planet Earth series -
全球野生动物的数量已经减少，
the abundance of wildlife around the globe has dropped,
平均而言，增幅超过30%。
on average, by over 30%.
我们正面临一场灾难，一场灾难。
We're facing a disaster, a catastrophe.
科学家称我们正处于大规模灭绝的边缘。
Scientists say that we're on the edge of a mass extinction.
这是由人类活动造成的。
It's being caused by human activity.
所以人类也有能力阻止它。
So humans also have the power to stop it.
即使拯救一个物种也需要具备多种品质。
It takes many qualities to save even one species.
决心...
Determination...
..勇气...
..courage...
..和热情。
..and passion.
通常，还需要另一种成分......
And often, there's another ingredient that's needed...
..大胆思考的能力。
..the ability to think big.
在维也纳，凯瑟琳娜·休克勒 (Katharina Huchler) 刚刚开始一份新工作。
In Vienna, Katharina Huchler is just starting a new job.
工资太可怕了。
The pay is terrible.
时间很长。
The hours are long.
而且没有休息日。
And there are no days off.
她即将成为一名养母。
She is about to become a foster mother.
你好。
Hi.
吱吱声
CHEEPING
早上好。
Good morning.
你好。 你好。
Hi. Hi.
这些是她的新生婴儿......
And these are her new babies...
哦。
Oh.
你很清醒。 你好。
You're pretty awake. Hi.
..28 世界上最稀有的鸟类之一。
..28 of one of the world's rarest birds.
嘿。 你好。
Hey. Hi.
北方秃鹮。
The northern bald ibis.
你真的很快就会爱上他们。
You really quickly fall in love with them.
凯瑟琳娜笑了
KATHARINA LAUGHS
400 多年前，它们在欧洲被猎杀至灭绝。
They were hunted to extinction in Europe over 400 years ago.
这些小鸡出生在动物园里。
These chicks were born in a zoo.
凯瑟琳娜的任务是教导他们
Katharina's task is to teach them
成为狂野、自由的鸟儿。
to become wild, free birds.
对对对。 科姆。 科姆。
Yes, yes, yes. Komm. Komm.
为此，她必须让他们相信她是他们的母亲。
To do that, she must convince them that she is their mother.
这是一个称为印记的过程。
It's a process called imprinting.
当事情发生时，小鸡们绝对不能看到或听到
While it's happening, the chicks must never see or hear
除海伦娜之外的任何其他人，
any other human except Helena,
她第二次成为宜必思寄养妈妈。
who's an ibis foster mum for the second time.
他们必须始终穿着相同的黄色衣服
They must always wear identical yellow clothes
并一次又一次地重复同样的声音。
and repeat the same noises again and again.
我们模仿成年人发出的声音，就像……
We mimic the sounds the adults make, it's like...
她的叫声沙哑
SHE MAKES HOARSE CALL
咕咕！
Kkrukk!
咕咕！ 克鲁普。
Kkrukk! Kklup.
克鲁普。 克鲁普。
Kklup. Kklup.
克鲁普。
Kklup.
但我还不太擅长做这件事！
But I'm not good yet at doing it!
他们笑了
THEY LAUGH
晚安。
Goodnight.
当小鸡们睡着的时候，他们就在这里……
They're here when the chicks fall asleep...
睡得好。
Sleep well.
..以及他们醒来时看到的第一件事。
..and the first thing they see when they awake.
早上好，华尔迪们！ 你好！
Good morning, waldies! Hallo!
我们吃点东西吧？ 是的，我们吃饭吧。
Let's have something to eat, shall we? Yes, let's eat.
他们有点像每个人类婴儿。
They're a bit like every human baby.
他们只需要一点一点的食物
They just need their food bit by bit by bit
整天。
all day long.
是的，是的，是的，是的，是的，是的。
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes.
哦，不，我们都做错了！
Oh, no, we did it all wrong!
哦！ 噢！
Oh! Aw!
这真的就像给婴儿换尿布一样。
It's really like changing the nappies of the babies.
28个嘴要喂，屁股要擦，
28 mouths to feed and bottoms to wipe,
并一直与鸟儿交谈。
and all the time talking to the birds.
科姆，科姆，华尔迪！ 科姆，科姆！
Komm, komm, waldies! Komm, komm!
感觉真的很累。
Feeling really tired.
是的，我真的很想多睡一会儿。
Yeah, I'd really like to sleep a little bit more.
几周过去了，两人之间的联系越来越紧密。
As the weeks pass, the bond grows.
然后是他们下一阶段的时间了
And then it is time for their next stage
成为野鸟。
in becoming wild birds.
他们搬到了奥地利阿尔卑斯山的一块田地。
They move to a field in the Austrian Alps.
它们现在已经长出了成年飞羽……
They've now grown their adult flight feathers...
......但他们的内心仍然是小鸡。
...but they're still chicks on the inside.
所以印记必须继续。
So the imprinting must continue.
我们用这个手势，
With this hand gesture we do,
我们模仿成年朱鹮的喙
we imitate the bill of an adult ibis
我们将它与问候声音结合起来。
and we combine it with the greeting sound.
所以，这是...
So, this is...
克鲁普！ 克鲁普！
Kklup! Kklup!
所有这些印记都有一个非常重要的原因。
All this imprinting is for a very important reason.
这些是候鸟。
These are migratory birds.
秋天，他们必须飞向南方
In autumn, they must fly south
到意大利温暖的觅食地。
to their warm feeding grounds in Italy.
这是一个问题。
And that is a problem.
他们知道他们需要去某个地方
They know that they need to go somewhere,
但他们不知道朝哪个方向、走多远。
but they don't know in which direction and how far.
所以他们需要向父母学习路线。
So they need to learn the route from their parents.
他们的人类母亲必须为他们指明道路。
Their human mothers must show them the way.
这需要一点聪明才智。
And that requires a little ingenuity.
发动机启动
ENGINE POWERS UP
这是对印记进行测试的地方。
This is where the imprinting is put to the test.
鸟儿会跟着他们吗...
Will the birds follow them...
..即使在微光下？
..even in a microlight?
凯瑟琳娜: 嗯，嗯！
KATHARINA: Komm, komm!
科姆，科姆，华尔迪！
Komm, komm, waldies!
科姆，科姆！
Komm, komm!
翻译:
TRANSLATION:
距离太近对鸟类和人类来说都是危险的。
Getting too close is dangerous for both birds and humans.
哦哦哦哦哦哦！
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh!
在经历了一段摇摇欲坠的开始之后……
After a wobbly start...
..最后他们安定下来。
..at last they settle.
印记已经发挥作用了。
The imprinting has worked.
我们的鸽子今天表现得很好。
Our birds did very well today.
但他们最大的挑战还在后头。
But their biggest challenge is still to come.
齐勒塔尔阿尔卑斯山。
The Zillertal Alps.
由岩石和冰组成的长城。
A great wall of rock and ice.
这将是最重要的航班
It's going to be the most important flight
他们年轻的生命。
of their young lives.
这将把他们带到精疲力竭的边缘。
It will take them to the very edge of exhaustion.
许多幼鸟在第一次迁徙期间死亡。
A lot of young birds die during their first migration.
他们还是那么缺乏经验。
They are still so inexperienced.
养母和飞行员也面临着危险。
There's also danger for the foster mothers and the pilots.
如果微灯出现问题，
If there is a problem with the microlights,
没有安全的着陆点。
there is no safe place to land.
为了获得足够的高度飞越这些山脉......
To gain enough height to fly over these mountains...
..他们必须找到称为热气流的上升气流。
..they must find columns of rising air called thermals.
这些鸟通常会学习的技能
A skill these birds would normally learn
跟随他们的亲生母亲。
by following their natural mothers.
风声
WIND WHISTLES
需要专业的驾驶才能找到热气流。
It takes expert piloting to find the thermals.
一旦在一内，
Once within one,
这是动荡和不可预测的。
it's turbulent and unpredictable.
每一次，妈妈们都必须确保
With every turn, the mothers must make sure
所有 28 只鸟都跟随。
all 28 birds are following.
所有 28 只鸟都在这里。
All 28 birds here.
唷。
Phew.
她如释重负地笑了
SHE LAUGHS IN RELIEF
最后，他们翻越了最高的山脊。
At last, they make it over the highest ridge.
从现在开始，飞行应该很容易。
From now on, it should be easy flying.
凯瑟琳娜:除了拯救朱鹮之外，我们正在努力做的事情
KATHARINA: What we are trying to do, apart from saving the ibis,
正在努力给人们带来希望。
is trying to give hope to people.
如果你能带回一种物种
If you can bring back one species,
你也可以和其他人一起做。
you can also do it with others.
曾经被遗弃的物种现在有了未来。
A species once left for dead now has a future.
他们前往安全的冬季家园
And they head for their safe winter home
在一个受保护的自然保护区。
in a protected nature reserve.
喇叭蜂鸣声
HORN BEEPS
但正如我们在本系列中所看到的，
But as we have seen throughout this series,
许多物种正在失去生存所需的野生栖息地。
many species are losing the wild habitats they need to survive.
这是灭绝的最大原因。
It's the biggest cause of extinction.
这一点在亚马逊雨林中表现得最为明显。
Nowhere is this more apparent than in the Amazon rainforest.
我们的《地球脉动》剧组曾多次在这里拍摄
Our Planet Earth crews have filmed here many times
在过去的二十年里。
over the last two decades.
木材嘎吱作响
TIMBER CREAKING
在那段时间里，超过 160 亿棵树......
And in that time, over 16,000 million trees...
..已经被砍倒了。
..have been felled.
为了保护生活在这里的无数物种......
To safeguard the countless species that live here...
..森林本身必须受到保护..
..the forest itself must be protected..
有一股力量正在兴起来做到这一点。
And there's a force rising up to do just that.
翻译:
TRANSLATION:
亚历山德拉·科拉普 (Alessandra Korap) 是蒙杜鲁库 (Munduruku) 的领导人之一。
Alessandra Korap is one of the leaders of the Munduruku.
他们一直是亚马逊这片地区的守护者
They have been the guardians of this part of the Amazon
千百年来。
for thousands of years.
当她还是个孩子的时候，亚马逊森林的这一部分
When she was a child, this part of the Amazon forest
绵延数百英里，绵延不绝。
stretched unbroken for hundreds of miles.
现在已经被瓜分了...
Now it's being carved up...
..用于采矿、木材、
..for mining, for timber,
但最重要的是农业。
but most of all for agriculture.
这是亚马逊争夺战的前线，
This is the front line in the battle for the Amazon,
这是致命的。
and it is a deadly one.
过去十年，超过300人被谋杀
In the last decade, more than 300 people have been murdered
在巴西保护环境。
in Brazil defending the environment.
蒙杜鲁库人，像许多土著群体一样，
The Munduruku, like many indigenous groups,
生活在偏僻的社区
live in isolated communities
容易受到矿工、农民和伐木者的攻击。
vulnerable to attack from miners, farmers and loggers.
亚马逊河的未来就在 2,000 英里之外决定。
The Amazon's future is decided 2,000 miles away.
在这里，在巴西议会，
Here, in the parliament of Brazil,
正在讨论允许剥削的新法律
new laws are being debated to allow the exploitation
他们的传统部落土地。
of their traditional tribal land.
但亚历山德拉有一个计划--
But Alessandra has a plan -
与其他部落联合
to unite with other tribes
并组织了如此大规模的抗议活动
and organise a protest so big
它不容忽视。
that it cannot be ignored.
这是前往首都的三天旅程。
It's a three-day journey to the capital city.
喇叭声
HORN BLARES
卡车隆隆地进出田野……
Trucks rumble to and from the fields...
..曾经是雨林的土地。
..land that used to be rainforest.
他们正在运送数千吨大豆。
They're carrying thousands of tonnes of soya beans.
它从亚马逊中心地带运往世界各地。
It's shipped from the heart of the Amazon across the world.
不是为了养活人类...
Not to feed humans...
..但要喂养牲畜。
..but to feed livestock.
最终，亚历山德拉抵达巴西利亚。
Eventually, Alessandra makes it to Brasilia.
抗议的消息已经传遍全国。
News of the protest has spread all over the country.
200个团体团结在一个巨大的营地里。
200 groups have united in a huge camp.
抗议者唱歌
PROTESTORS SING
来自巴西东北部的Xukuru。
From the northeast of Brazil - the Xukuru.
来自亚马逊南部边缘 - 卡拉贾。
From the southern edge of the Amazon - the Karaja.
他们抗议拟议的法律长达十天。
For ten days, they protest against the proposed laws.
亚历山德拉和其他领导人创造了
Alessandra and the other leaders have created
巴西有史以来最大规模的原住民抗议活动。
the biggest protest by indigenous people ever held in Brazil.
后来，其中一项拟议的法律被撤回。
Later, one of the proposed laws was withdrawn.
虽小但意义重大的胜利
A small but significant victory
亚历山德拉为巴西荒野而战。
in Alessandra's fight for Brazil's wild places.
栖息地破坏是目前最大的威胁
The destruction of habitats is currently the biggest threat
为了动物物种的生存。
to the survival of animal species.
但更大的灾难即将来临。
But there is an even greater disaster on the horizon.
我们的气候正在发生变化。
Our climate is changing.
季节变得不可预测且更加极端。
Seasons have become unpredictable and more extreme.
我们的星球正在变得越来越热。
Our planet is getting hotter.
科学家预测，如果全球气温升高
Scientists predict that if the global temperature
上升超过两度，
rises by over two degrees,
它很可能成为灭绝的头号原因。
it is likely to become the number one cause of extinction.
为了阻止气候变化，
To halt climate change,
也许政治家也需要成为英雄。
perhaps politicians need to become heroes, too.
记者:大家好，晚上好，热烈欢迎来到格拉斯哥
REPORTER: Hello, good evening, and a warm welcome to Glasgow
以及期待已久的气候峰会 COP26 的开始。
and the start of the long-awaited climate summit, COP26.
世界领导人、杰出科学家
World leaders, prominent scientists
和顾问们都已准备好迎接 12 天的...
and advisers all ready for 12 days of...
穆罕默德·纳希德是一位政治家，
Mohamed Nasheed is a politician,
马尔代夫前总统。
the former president of the Maldives.
穆罕默德:医生说他们拿走了 16 个滚珠轴承
MOHAMED: The doctors said that they took 16 ball bearings
来自我身体的各个部位。
from all parts of my body.
我昏迷了两天。
I was unconscious for two days.
在他的政治生涯中，他遭受过酷刑、监禁
Over his political career, he has been tortured, imprisoned
最近在一次暗杀行动中幸存下来。
and recently survived an assassination attempt.
但那段时间，
But during that time,
他还不懈地与气候变化作斗争。
he's also fought relentlessly against climate change.
..很高兴能够为您带来穆罕默德·纳希德。
..pleasure to be able to bring you Mohamed Nasheed.
观众欢呼
AUDIENCE CHEERS
在格拉斯哥气候大会 COP26 召开前夕，
In Glasgow, on the eve of climate conference COP26,
他正在一次集会上发表讲话。
he is addressing a rally.
谢谢。
Thank you.
非常感谢。
Thank you very much.
所以，我们来到了 COP26
So, we come to COP26
看看我们是否还有未来。
to find out whether we still have a future.
如果我们无法达成具有法律约束力的协议
If we cannot have a legally binding agreement
不要推高全球气温
not to push global temperatures
1.5度以上，
above 1.5 degrees,
我的国家将会消失
my country will be gone,
世界上所有的珊瑚礁也一样
as will all the world's coral reefs
和大部分雨林。
and most of the rainforests.
这一切的破坏真的值得吗
Is all this devastation really worth it,
这样我们就可以继续燃烧煤炭和化石燃料
so that we can continue to burn coal and fossil fuel
再过几年？
for a few more years?
我用了一生
I have spent a lifetime
为我的国家而战，
fighting for my country,
并以比以往更加坚定的决心，
and with more determination than ever,
因为我知道我在地球上的时间可能会缩短。
because I know my time on Earth might be cut short.
穆罕默德·纳希德对自然世界的热情
Mohamed Nasheed's passion for the natural world
开始于他第一次看到珊瑚礁。
began the first time he saw a coral reef.
穆罕默德:我最早的记忆
MOHAMED: My earliest memory
与海洋和珊瑚礁在一起。
is with the ocean and the reef.
我们是第一代真正看到珊瑚礁的人。
We were the first generation to actually see the reef.
口罩和护目镜来到马尔代夫
Masks and goggles came to the Maldives
60年代末、70年代初。
in the late '60s, early '70s.
一旦我们开始将珊瑚礁视为一个生物......
Once we started seeing the reef as a living creature...
..我们只是傻眼了。
..we were just dumbfounded.
但纳希德心爱的珊瑚现在成了栖息地
But Nasheed's beloved coral is now the habitat
这是受气候变化威胁最大的国家。
that is most threatened by climate change.
临界临界点是温度升高 1.5 度。
The critical tipping point is a 1.5 degree temperature rise.
除此之外，大多数珊瑚礁都会死亡，
Beyond that, most reefs will die,
除了瓦砾什么也没有留下。
leaving nothing but rubble.
当你想到更大的图景时，
When you think of a bigger picture,
那么你自己的生活就不那么重要了。
then your own life is not so important.
这是你想要完成的事情，这很重要。
It's what you want to get done which is important.
纳希德的目标是说服政客减少使用
Nasheed's aim is to persuade politicians to cut the use
煤炭和其他化石燃料。
of coal and other fossil fuels.
他在每次气候会议上都会重复这一呼吁。
He repeats this plea at every climate conference.
你需要能够说服人们，
You need to be able to convince people,
尝试教育人们。
try to educate people.
我们有麻烦了。
We are in trouble.
如果地球温度超过 1.5 度，我们将无法生存。
We will not survive if the planet is heated above 1.5 degrees.
我们必须立即行动。
We must act now.
一开始，记者们正在报道一些引人注目的承诺
At first, journalists are reporting on some eye-catching promises
由国家元首制定。
made by heads of state.
记者:18个国家已做出承诺
REPORTER: 18 countries have committed themselves
停止使用燃煤发电厂的计划。
to a plan to stop using coal-fired power plants.
现在这是一个选举问题。
It is an election issue now.
这就是世界领导人加入这一言论的原因。
That is why world leaders have joined the rhetoric.
下一阶段--将承诺转化为切实的计划。
The next stage - turning promises into solid plans.
而纳希德则忙于幕后工作。
And Nasheed is busy working behind the scenes.
如果他们不同意，我们会打电话给他们的部长、总统
If they don't agree, we will ring their ministers, their presidents
并让他们上网。
and get them online.
我认为这就是我们正在努力做的事情。
I think that's what we're trying to do.
那么让我们这样做吧。
So let's do this.
总理，你好吗？
How are you, Prime Minister?
是的，好的。 我可以听见你，
Yeah, OK. I can hear you,
但我能更清楚地听到总理的话。
but I can hear the Prime Minister much clearer.
所有国家都需要就最终文本达成一致 -
All countries need to agree to the final text -
有些人不会。
and some won't.
想要继续使用化石燃料的人们，
People who want to continue fossil fuel,
我想，都是坏人。
I think, are the bad guys.
我觉得那些想要改变的人都是好人。
And people who want to change, I feel, are the good guys.
谢谢。 太感谢了。
Thank you. Thank you so much.
14 天后，本次 COP 结束...
After 14 days, this COP closes...
..有了一些进展，
..with some progress,
但也有很大的妥协。
but also with big compromises.
新闻阅读器:今晚终于达成协议
NEWSREADER: An agreement was finally reached this evening
在关于煤炭未来使用的关键部分之后
after a key section on the future use of coal
在最后一刻被淡化了。
was at the last moment watered down.
如果没有紧急的新承诺，
Without urgent new commitments,
1.5度的目标将无法实现。
the target of 1.5 degrees will be missed.
这是灾难性的。
It is disastrous.
它会...
It will...
如果你想象这个，如果你能理解它......
If you picture this, if you can fathom it...
..珊瑚会白化
..the coral will bleach
他们将会死去，
and they will die,
当他们死后，
and when they are dead,
生活在那里的鱼和海洋生物......
the fish and the marine life that lives there...
..不复存在。
..cease to exist.
你可能会认为你的正常首相
You would have thought that your normal prime minister
还有总统……
and president...
..会更好地理解事物。
..would have a better grip on understanding things.
不只是不断地继续
And not just go on and on and on
关于保护他们的生活方式。
about protecting their way of life.
所以看到政客们真是令人沮丧……
So it's frustrating to see politicians...
..谁似乎不明白。
..who doesn't seem to understand it.
就目前的政策来看，
With current policies,
99%的珊瑚礁可能消失...
99% of coral reefs could be gone...
..不到30年。
..in under 30 years.
其他栖息地也会随之而来。
Other habitats will follow.
你不能失去希望。
You can't lose hope.
你不能放弃。
You cannot give up.
我不会停止。
I will not stop.
纳希德相信有一个解决方案。
Nasheed believes there is a solution.
环境越成为选举问题，
The more environment becomes an election issue,
将会有更多针对气候的行动。
there will be more action on climate.
每次你投票，每次选举，
Every time you vote, in every election,
请勾选这个星球。
please tick the planet.
拯救物种的挑战不能留给少数人
The challenge of saving species can't be left to a few
克服困难的英雄人物。
heroic individuals working against the odds.
这是那些拥有强大权力的人
It's those in positions of great power
谁能发挥最大作用。
who can make the most difference.
因此，最终，他们必须承担最大的责任。
So, ultimately, it is they who must take the most responsibility.
也许我们的角色之一就是让他们承担责任。
Perhaps one of our roles is to hold them to account.
对于许多物种来说，时间已经不多了，
Time is running out for many species,
但我坚信如果现在做出正确的决定
but I truly believe that if the right decisions are made now,
在这个关键时刻，
at this critical moment,
所有生命仍可能有光明的未来
there could still be a bright future for all life
在我们美好的地球上。
on our wonderful planet Earth.
栖息地探索者让动物及其栖息地栩栩如生。
Habitat Explorer brings animals and their habitats to life.
探索这个免费的互动，并制作折纸动物。
Explore this free interactive, and make origami animals.
访问 bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
Go to bbc.co.uk/planetearth3
并点击开放大学的链接。
and follow the links to the Open University.
或者订购免费印刷版，
Or to order a free printed version,
访问网站或拨打屏幕上的号码。
visit the website or call the numbers on the screen.